A Finding Aid to the John Marshall Papers, 1960s-2000s, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
John Marshall papers
1960s-2000s
Archives of American Art
Marshall, John, 1936-
AAA.marsjohn
Archival Resource Key
2.1 Linear feet
The papers of artist and educator John Marshall measure 2.1 linear feet and date from the 1960s to early 2000s. The collection sheds light on Marshall's career through professional files, photographs, and artwork. Professional files include resumes, awards and certificates, professional correspondence, some project files, printed material, two scrapbooks, and a film reel. Photographs consist of slides of Marshall's work and his artwork series, some of which depict Marshall working in his studio. Also found are transparencies of his work and exhibition displays; scant candid and portrait snapshots of the artist; and mounted photographs of his work. Artwork found in the collection is mostly design sketches of metalwork projects for jewlery, pots, cups, and silverware done in charcoal and pencil; and two paintings.
Biographical / Historical
John Marshall (1936- ) is a metalsmith and educator in Edmonds, Washington. Marshall was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 1936. His interest in art began at approximately the fifth grade, when both he and his brother received scholarships to Saturday drawing classes at the Carnegie Museum. Marshall then entered into the U.S. Army following high school, for which he served primarily in Germany until 1957. Able to travel around during this time, Marshall became more interested in metalworking and other forms of art. After the military, Marshall returned to Pennsylvania to attend Grove City College and work construction, specifically pipelining. He ultimately transfered to Carnegie Tech (now part of Carnegie Melon University). In 1960 he began school at the Cleveland Institute of Art, learning from Kenneth Bates, John Paul Miller, and John Clague, and alongside Winifred Lutz. He received his B.F.A. from Cleveland in 1965.
Marshall received a teaching position as head of Syracuse University's metals program. Once there, Marshall worked with Laurence Schmeckebier to complete his M.F.A.; Schmeckbier was also instrumental in exhibiting Marshall's artwork at this time. Looking to establish himself as a metalsmith, he became associated with others in his field such as Olaf Skoogfors, Fred Fenster, and Stanley Lechtzin, and became involved with the Soceity of North American Goldsmiths. After his time in Syracuse, Marshall went to the University of Washington in 1970 where he remained for the rest of his teaching career.
Marshall has held one-man shows at the Lowe Art Center, Syracuse University, Henry Art Gallery, University of Washington, and Concepts Gallery in California; and has had his work featured in group shows at the Museum of Concemporary Crafts, Renwick Gallery, and the Laguna Art Museum. He has received many public and private commissions throughout his career to create trophies, cups, bowls, and sculptures, most notably a 16-foot sculpture for the United Methodist Church in Edmonds, Washington.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as three series.
Series 1: Professional Files, 1967-2000s (Box 1, FC 9; .5 linear feet)
Series 2: Photographs, 1960s-2000s (Box 1-2, 4, OV 6; .7 linear feet)
Series 3: Artwork, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 5, OV 7-8; .8 linear feet)
Scope and Contents
The papers of artist and educator John Marshall measure 2.1 linear feet and date from the 1960s to early 2000s. The collection sheds light on Marshall's career through professional files, photographs, and artwork. Professional files include resumes, awards and certificates, professional correspondence, some project files, printed material, two scrapbooks, and a film reel. Photographs consist of slides of Marshall's work and his artwork series, some of which depict Marshall working in his studio. Also found are transparencies of his work and exhibition displays; scant candid and portrait snapshots of the artist; and mounted photographs of his work. Artwork found in the collection is mostly design sketches of metalwork projects for jewlery, pots, cups, and silverware done in charcoal and pencil; and two paintings.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2004 by John Marshall as part of the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Drawings; Video recordings; Silversmiths -- Washington (State); Metals; Motion pictures; Society of North American Goldsmiths; Syracuse University -- Faculty; University of Washington -- Faculty; Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America
- Professional Files, 1967-2000s; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1, FC 9
  Scope and Contents
  Found here are resumes, awards and certificates Marshall revieved from professional organizations and colleges, letters sent by universities and museums to thank Marshall for lectures and workshop preseentations he gave, documentation on donations of work, and exhibition records. Also found are a statement, description, and printed material related to Marshall's enamel plaque for the Edmonds United Methodist Church; printed material from exhibitions, publicity campaigns, and clippings; and two scrapbooks composed of printed material, awards, correspondence, and some photographs. The collection also includes a film reel that contains footage from a promotional film created by the Society of North American Goldsmiths. The footage depicts metalsmiths in their studios as well as examples of their work.
  - "A Point of View", 1995 December 20; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Cerificates, 1973, 1980, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Enamel Plaque for Edmonds United Methodist Church, 1978, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New Works by John Marshall (1998), Exhibition Essay by Dana Standish, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material, Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1973-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, Artist Publicity Package, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, Solo Exhibition Material, 1967-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Printed Material, Group Exhibition Material, 1970s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Printed Material, Syracuse University Press Release Regarding the "Chapel Cup", 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed Material, Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Resumes, 1990s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1963-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1970-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
  - Society of North American Goldsmiths, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 9)
    Promotional Film
  - Society of North American Goldsmiths, Film Papers, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stationery; Card, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs, 1960s-2000s; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1-2, 4, OV 6
  This series contains slides of Marshall's artwork series, some of which depict Marshall working in his studio; transparencies of his work and exhibition displays; scant candid and portrait snapshots of the artist; and mounted photographs of various works by Marshall.
  - Johnson in Studio, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Artwork, Slides, 1960s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Artwork, Transparencies; One Photograph, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, Transparemcies, circa 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mounted Photographs of Artwork, circa 1980s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
  - Mounted Photographs of Artwork, circa 1980s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
- Artwork, circa 1970s-2000s; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Box 5, OV 7-8
  Artwork includes mostly oversized design sketches of jewelry, pots, cups, and silverware done in charcoal and pencil. Some of the sketches are in color, but the marjority of them are black and white. Also present are two paintings of Marshall's, xeroxes, and one presentation board of a drawn teapot design.
  - Charcoal Sketches, circa 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Charcoal Sketches, circa 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Paintings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Pencil Sketches, circa 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Project Sketches, circa 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 8)
  - Teapot Presentation Board with Drawings and Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Xeroxes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)